<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Answer to a scandalous paper, wherein were some queries given to be answered. And likewise, therein is found many lies and slanders, and false accusations against those people whom he (and the world) calls Quakers. Dated from Dorchester in New-England, August 17. 1655. subscribed, Edward Breck, which was directed to a people at Rainforth in Lancashire, which he calls, A church of Christ. The truth is cleared of his scandalls, lies, and slanders, and he found to bee a reproacher of the Church of Christ. His paper and quæries answered by those people called, Quakers.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75414</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3345A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E875_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206566</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865691</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865691</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117940</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75414)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117940)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 132:E875[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Answer to a scandalous paper, wherein were some queries given to be answered. And likewise, therein is found many lies and slanders, and false accusations against those people whom he (and the world) calls Quakers. Dated from Dorchester in New-England, August 17. 1655. subscribed, Edward Breck, which was directed to a people at Rainforth in Lancashire, which he calls, A church of Christ. The truth is cleared of his scandalls, lies, and slanders, and he found to bee a reproacher of the Church of Christ. His paper and quæries answered by those people called, Quakers.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 3-4, 3-24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the Black Spread-Eagle neer the west end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A2r-B2r consist of Breck's "paper".</note>
                  <note>"An ansvver to a scandalous paper" has caption title on B3r.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "14 Aprill".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Breck, Edward. --  To the Church of Christ at Rainforth --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117940:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO A SCANDALOUS PAPER, Wherein were ſome QUERIES Given to be anſwered. And likewiſe, Therein is found many Lies and Slanders, and falſe Accuſations againſt thoſe people whom he (and the World) calls <hi>Quakers.</hi> Dated from <hi>Dorcheſter</hi> in <hi>New-England, Auguſt</hi> 17. 1655. ſubſcribed, <hi>Edward Breck,</hi> which was directed to a People at <hi>Rainforth</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> which he calls, <hi>A Church of Chriſt.</hi> The Truth is cleared of his Scandalls, Lies, and Slanders, and he found to bee a Reproacher of the <hi>Church of Chriſt. His Paper and Quaeries anſwered by thoſe people cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> QUAKERS.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 15.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The reproaches of them that reproached thee fell on mee.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 52.14, 15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>His viſage was ſo marred more than any man, and his form more than the ſons of men. So ſhall he ſprinckle many Nations; Kings ſhall ſhut their mouths at him, for that which had not been told them ſhall they ſee, and that which they had not heard ſhall they conſider.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 5.11, 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Bleſſed are yee when men ſhall revile you, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute you, and ſay all manner of evill againſt you falſly for my names ſake. Rejoyce, and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in heaven, for ſo perſecuted they the Prophets which went before you.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the Black Spread-Eagle neer the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:117940:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117940:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Edward Breek</hi> to the Church of CHRIST at <hi>RAINFORTH.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>DEerly beloved in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, I have ſundrytimes had a mind to ſalute you in the Lord, but partly my own rudeneſs, and partly other obſtacles in the way, I have not yet communicated any thing to you, as to the Church of Chriſt ſince my departing; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath removed me ſo far diſtant, by reaſon whereof I am never like to ſee your faces, and age and weakneſs coming upon me, putting me in minde of my end; that I might do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at laſt whereby to teſtifie my love &amp; dear reſpects to you, and that in all this length of time of abſence, you might perceive that I have not wholly forgotten you, but with many ſecret deſires breathed after your eternal welfares; I have therefore for your ſakes, preſſed my ſelf to break through many difficulties, preſuming up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your kind acceptance, notwithſtanding you finde in me much weakneſs in expreſſion, mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, argument, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But not to trouble you with a long Preface, where my work is ſmall, little I have to ſay, and ſlenderly I ſhal deliver it, unleſs God make known his power through weaknes; that which I have to ſay is a friendly exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to continue in the <hi>grace and faith of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and not to be carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with every winde of Doctrine, whereby you ſhould be ſpoiled of your <hi>faith and hope</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:117940:3"/>which you have in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: Oh Beloved! Remember the dayes of old, and the yeers of ancient times, when after the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian-times</hi> that Religion began to ſpring God ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured <hi>Rainforth</hi> with many godly pillars, men famous in their days, for faith and holineſs, and the profeſſion of true Religion, when the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try was overwhelmed, or greatly clouded with Religion, or Superſtition, yet theſe men (whoſe names are not yet worn out of memory) cleave faſt to the truth; the face of oppoſing, jeering, ſcorning and reproaching enemies, their reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches did not dant the ſpirits of theſe men, but they patiently bare it with joy, and preſt on forward in the waies of Truth of the Goſpel, <hi>for the price and high calling of God in Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> The next Generation I was a little better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with, whoſe names are freſher in your memories, divers godly people God raiſed up to do him ſome <hi>Service,</hi> and to profeſs and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his <hi>Truth,</hi> &amp; maintain his <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> which was a great thing they laboured after; theſe <hi>men</hi> gave not their mindes with <hi>Balaam,</hi> to <hi>look out for viſions,</hi> to <hi>curſe Gods People,</hi> nor to <hi>rail on Magiſtracy, nor Miniſtry,</hi> but <hi>humbly</hi> and <hi>in the feare of the Lord, ſubmitted themſelves to Ieſus Chriſt in the uſe of his owne Inſtitutions, ſo farre as he gave them liberty and ability thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, what the preſent <hi>Generation</hi> is ſince I left the Countrey, I do not ſo well know, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the old ſtock being dead and removed;
<pb facs="tcp:117940:3"/>yet (I hope) there is ſome breathing of <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual life</hi> amongſt you, and <hi>men bolding forth the faith, and profeſsion of faith and true Religion in ſincerity,</hi> notwithſtanding what may be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe found among you: My Exhortation therefore is, <hi>To hold forth this Faith, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue faithfull therein untill Death, never leave it, forſake it not leſt God forſake you, and cast you off for ever;</hi> but Truth is Beloved, and that which is my griefe, that I have been informed, and dare not but believe it, that there are men among you who are departed from the faith and purity of the Goſpel to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon Jeſuiticall and Satannical deluſions, I mean ſuch as go under the name of <hi>QUA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KERS,</hi> who depend not upon the Scriptures, for Light, but on what they receive from a Spirit which caſteth them into a Trance, what theſe Trances are, let men of underſtanding judge, for I am weak, onely tell you what I think, they are either from the good Spirit of GOD, as hee ſpake by the mouth of his holy Prophets in Viſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or from the DEVILL; if they bee from the good Spirit of GOD, then they are like to that Spirit which ſpake by the PROPHETS, they accord with all the writings of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and moſt of all with all the doctrins and ſayings of Jeſus Chriſt, his <hi>Ordinances</hi> and <hi>Inſtitutions.</hi> Secondly, they bring a man that receive them, into a humble, low, and meane eſteeme of HIMSELFE,
<pb facs="tcp:117940:4"/>ſo that he will be ready to fall down with the Prophet, <hi>Eſay</hi> 6.5. and to cry, <hi>Wo is me, I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, becauſe I am a man of unclean lips, and I dwell among men of unclean lips, for my eyes have ſeen the King the Lord of Hoſts;</hi> his neer approach to God laid him low, but for brevities ſake, I give you no more Arguments, but let the ſpirits of theſe <hi>Quakers</hi> be tried a little by theſe brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Doth that ſpirit which caſts you into your trances make you like the old Prophets? Doth it accord with the Law, and Teſtimony? with Moſes and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets? with the Writings of the holy Apoſtles, and the Doctrines of Chriſt, his Orders and Inſtitution?</hi> then ſomething might be favourably ſpoken in defence and excuſe thereof; but if on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the ſpirit which bringeth you into your Trances, when your bones quake, and you think you hear the voice of God, if the revelations and viſions of this ſpirit ſpeak contrary to the Prophets and Apoſtles, yea ſometimes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict and blaſpheme, yea and ſometimes amongſt your ſelves be contrary to your owne viſions; yea, if this ſpirit when you ſpeak, teach you to ſpeak non-ſenſe, idle, redicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and fooliſh things, bee ſaid falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and contradictions, if it provoke you to ſpeak blaſphemouſly againſt the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, crying downe his Inſtitutions, as Magiſtracy, Miniſtry, Sacraments, Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> let me ask you, Did that ſpirit ever proceed from the Father and the Son, that breathed out Blaſphemies in his face? Judge
<pb facs="tcp:117940:4"/>in your ſelves. You think it is no blaſphemy, but I pray conſider it, Chriſt held forth in his Ordinances he breatheth in them, and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the middeſt of the <hi>Golden Candleſticks,</hi> conveying his heavenly Grace through them as through ſo many golden pipes: Now to have Magiſtracy, and Miniſtery, Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſpoken againſt, trodden underfoot, and held in contempt, and eſteemed as very ſleight and ſlender things, and thoſe that cleave to the Scriptures and Ordinances to be accounted as Antichriſtian, Carnall, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I pray you whom doth this ſtrike? on whom doth it light, if not on Chriſt the Author? and is it not then Blaſphemy? what do you call it? You may try a little what ſpirit it is that ſets you into your trances by the effects, if your ſpirit make you more ſenſible of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall ſin, more ſenſible of your own vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, more humble you, and caſt you down in the ſight of God, and ſay you low, ſo that you can cry out with <hi>Job, Behold I am vile, what ſhall I anſwer thee?</hi> and with <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiah</hi> cry out, <hi>Woe is mee, I am undone, Iſa.</hi> 6.5. then it were conſiderable; but if on the contrary, it make the heart ſwell, and to cry, <hi>Stand apart, I am more holy then thou;</hi> and all that come not up to your at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments are of ſmall value, little worth, juſt as the Phariſees, who truſted in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that they were righteous, and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed others: If I ſay it be thus, then judge you
<pb facs="tcp:117940:5"/>what ſpirit it is, I dare be bold to affirm, it is the Spirit of Satan, and not of God; you may think this haſtily, and ſuddenly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude; and I confeſs, I have not waded very deep into this matter, yet what is not from God I can eaſily conclude it is from the Devil, or man corruption, which is no better, I know no <hi>medium,</hi> unleſs it be the Jeſuits, who no doubt have had a large hand this way by their ſorceries to deceive the people, and have been known in <hi>London</hi> to quake and ſpeak in the Congregations; theſe men (it is little doubt) might make a covenant with the Devil, &amp; in the fineſt way of <hi>witchcraft</hi> &amp; <hi>ſorceries</hi> convene it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver unto others; by an implicite covenant ſeduce men, thinking no ſuch thing, but rather as though God had more abundantly declared his love to them more then to any people in the world, whenas indeed the matter is nothing els but Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan transformed into an Angel of light; for this purpoſe let me make bold to report unto you this ſtory which is credibly reported to have been in or about <hi>Briſtol,</hi> There was a mans wife deſired to go to one of the <hi>Quakers</hi> meetings, her husband was unwilling, but after importunity he gave her leave, but ſhe was ſo wrought upon in that meeting, that when ſhe came home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine ſhee was filled with REVELATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS, and ſpoke as though ſhee had ſpoke with the Tongue of <hi>ANGELS,</hi> to admiration farre above her ſelfe, her HVSBAND told her, ſhe was bewitched,
<pb facs="tcp:117940:5"/>ſhe was far enough from believing that, but he could not ſatisfie himſelf, but would ſearch her body, to ſee what tokens he could find, &amp; about her arm he found a ſilk thred; he inquired, how that came there; ſhe ſeriouſly confeſsed, ſhe knew nothing of it; well, ſaith he, this ſhall not remain here; then they took it away, and then ſhe returned to be the ſame woman that ſhee was before ſhe went to the Quakers Meeting: If this be a true Story, as I credibly believe, tell me, if there were witchcraft uſed in this Quakers meeting, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p>Oh Beloved! you may well think the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil hath a finer way of witchcraft now, then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he had ſince the world began; no doubt yee can very well paint men to come to the Lords Table, and to preach Chriſt, for he hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time been a Preacher of Chriſt himſelf, you know, for no good will to Chriſt, you may be ſure; but who are they that are moſt apart to be taken? Are they men who of old hath been moſt neer to God, and walked before God, as our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Abraham</hi> did, and <hi>lived the life of faith and holineſs,</hi> and <hi>injoyed many ſweet, and pleaſant Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquies, peace and joy in believing, and many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable conſolations?</hi> I am apt to think few of theſe men are taken, if any at all; but rather, <hi>fickle minded men, unconſtant, and unſtable in their ways,</hi> ſuch as perhaps, do change their God and Religion divers times, or proud perſons, ſuch as affect ſingularity to be alone, &amp; think it a brave thing to be taken up with Rapters above other
<pb facs="tcp:117940:6"/>men, who but they in the world &amp; in the mean time, who more proud, more fickle, and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, more wrathful &amp; paſſionate, more railing &amp; blaſpheming? can you think the Spirit of God doth cloſe better with thoſe men then anyother? Truly no: And what can you imagine wil be the iſſue, after a curſe driven this way? a certain time truly it is probable their works wilbe made manifeſt, &amp; the tree wil be known by its fruit, if it be not already a little; I have learned what befel <hi>Grinton,</hi> a people come up to Trances and Revelations, fel at laſt to Popery and prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as I have been informed, and Popery I think is the main thing the Devil drives at now, rather I think, becauſe the Jeſuits hath been the chief fomenters of this <hi>Quaking Religion,</hi> and how do you finde it for the preſent in theſe people? do you often ſee them upon their knees? bewailing their ſin? fill'd with godly ſorrow &amp; repenting-hearts? a thing God much delights in; with hearts weary and heavy laden, ſuch as Chriſt calls to come unto him? do you finde them fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in Familie-Duties, Catechizing, praying, &amp;c. if you do, I ſhall be glad to hear it, and how it is I will not cenſure; but if you find it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then confider what fruit it is. Oh beloved! what ſhall I ſay? my hearts deſire is, that you may be eſtabliſh't in the faith of Gods elect, and that thoſe that are already deluded may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, and that all men may prevent the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; if what I have ſaid be but ſlender, as well it may be, that which I ſhall ſay can be but of
<pb facs="tcp:117940:6"/>like nature: Yet if I may not weary you too much, I would propoſe ſome Quaeries to theſe men, and preſent the matter to conſideration in another view. 1 Qu. <hi>By whom do you hope to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved?</hi> My charity bids me make your anſwer, <hi>By Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God, who alſo in time became man, and made ſatisfaction to divine juſtice for the ſin of his people, &amp;c.</hi> I hope you will accept my Anſwer. 2 Qu. <hi>How came you to know there was ever ſuch a man in the world?</hi> Here alſo I will preſume to anſwer for you, <hi>By the Prophets which went before him, and by the witneſs of his holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and Evangeliſts, who have left the Story in their holy record of the new Teſtament.</hi> I truſt you will not deny this neither. 3 Qu. <hi>If Chriſt be the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and that the light and knowledg of him do ſpring from holy Scriptures, I ask, whether the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures be any rule of Faith and Life in theſe days? Or are they abrogated, and put an end to by Chriſt, and hath he appointed another way for bringing his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to eternal life and ſalvation?</hi> This Queſtion I muſt leave you to anſwer your ſelves, onely for my part, I know no other way whereby to come to Chriſt my Saviour, then the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which he hath commanded me to ſearch, and which hee promiſed eternal life, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. and whereof he curſeth all men that addeth to them, or detracteth from them, <hi>Revelations</hi> 21. What you have to ſay to theſe things I know not, but theſe things I know; and this I know, that no man ſpeaking by the Spirit of God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Jeſus execrable, and what they do leſs that
<pb facs="tcp:117940:7"/>vilifie and ſlight his Word and Ordinances, and upon a Spirit which croſſeth and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicteth Chriſt, and his Word and Ordinances; but I weary you too much, I ſhall leave this <hi>Quaking Religion</hi> to its tottering, untill it fall to its utter Ruin, which will be in Gods due time accompliſh't, onely one word more, my Dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Boloved, as I earneſtly deſire you to take heed of this <hi>Quaking Religion,</hi> ſo alſo of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sects and Schiſmes, Errors, and Hereſies, whatſoever, and to ſettle your ſelves in the Faith and holy Order of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt; to worſhip and ſerve him according to his appointment, but what that is I determine not, but whether <hi>Presbyterian</hi> or <hi>Independant,</hi> as many uſe terms which are better forborn, as God ſhall guide your Judgements, ſo walk in holineſs of life, and beware of corrupt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; I have heard of too much that way, ſundry, if not many, given up to laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſneſs, Covetouſneſs, Drunkenneſs, Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Tiplings dayly, to the waſting of their Eſtates, and Ruine of their own ſouls: Take heed, take heed, O beloved take heed; I ſhall not need I hope to oppreſs you with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny words, you have the LAW of GOD ingraven upon your hearts, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinceth your Conſciences here, and will Judge you at the laſt Day, if Repentance prevent not; But <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſay no more, but commend you to GOD and to the WORD of his GRACE, which is able
<pb facs="tcp:117940:7"/>to build you up further, and to give you an inheritance among them that are ſanctified. The Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt be with you all, and alway: Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your old Friend, and Brother in the Lord Ieſus, Edward Breck.</signed>
               <dateline>Dor cheſter, <hi>in</hi> New-England, <date>
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> 17. 1655.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:117940:8"/>
            <head>AN ANSVVER TO A SCANDALOUS PAPER, Wherein were ſome QUERIES Given to be anſwered, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>PAPER we have received, in which we finde much Confuſion, Lyes and Slanders, and falſe Accuſations, which hath come from the dark carnall minde, which is enmitie with God, which knoweth not the living God (who is a God of Truth.) Therefore for the ſimple ones ſake, which maybe deceived by believing ſuch Lyes and Slanders which is caſt upon the Truth by the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of God; and for the clearing of the pure Truth of God, we, who are witneſſes for the living, and true God, againſt all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and powers of hell and death, are made free to anſwer this Paper, according to the Eternall Truth, as it is in Jeſus.</p>
            <p>And firſt, Thou Writes to the Church of Chriſt (as thou calls it) in <hi>Rainſorth,</hi> and thou confeſſeth thy own <hi>Rudeneſs,</hi> and <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and other <hi>Obſtacles,</hi> &amp;c. We anſwer, That thou who art in <hi>Rudeneſs,</hi> and <hi>weakneſs</hi> art not fit to communicate any thing to the Church of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> For the Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is pure, <hi>without ſpot or wrinckle,</hi> and will receive nothing from thy <hi>rudeneſs</hi> and <hi>weakneſs,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117940:8"/>and ſo thou might have ſpared thy breath and thy pen. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as thou ſaith, <hi>that age and weakneſs is coming upon thee, putting thee in minde of thy end:</hi> Here thou may be a Witneſs againſt thy ſelf, that thou art not fit to communicate to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when as thou doeſt no better conſider in this thy old age, thy own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that thou art to give at the Throne of Grace, where thou muſt give an account for evere idle word, and every lye, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtander and falſe accuſation which thou haſt caſt upon the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent in this thy Paper, for which the Lord God will plead with thee, for all thy hard ſpeeches, which thou haſt ſpoken againſt the harmleſs and innocent people, which thou knows nothing by, nor of, but what thou haſt from lying Reports: therefore under the wo thou haſt brought thy ſelf, which <hi>Iude</hi> ſpeaks of, who ſpeaks evill of the things which thou knows not, and therefore hath in theſe things corrupted thy ſelf: And this (thou ſaith) is the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of thy love, which thou wilt do at the laſt for the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and now here thou haſt treaſured up Wrath againſt the day of Wrath, which thou ſhall finde recorded, never to be forgotten, when thou cometh to reckon with the juſt and righteous God, who can by no means clear the guilty.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou exhorts them to continue in the faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ask thee what faith that is that thou would have them to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in? if it be thy faith, it is to beleeve lyes, (as thou confeſſeth in thy Paper) which is come ſo far as <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Briſtol</hi> to thee to <hi>New-England,</hi> which is a publique and generall Faith, ſuch a Faith as never any ſuffered for in the <hi>Marian</hi>-times (which thou ſpeaks of:) Therefore thy Faith, which is founded upon ſuch a foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (as a refuge of Lyes) is not fit to exhort the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> neither will the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> receive thy Exhortation, but turn it back upon thee from whence it came; and the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> exhorts thee to beware of beleeving lyes, and caſting Reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es upon the Truth of God, which went ever under Reproach and Scandall, which <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> who is the Captain of our ſalvation, gave the bleſſing to thoſe that were reproached, whom all men ſpoke evill of, and perſecuted, which now we, (who are the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>) witneſs fulfilled at this day; but Reproaches is our Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and all that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, muſt ſuffer perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution by this Generation which thou art of, who are given up to beleeve lyes: And herein we follow him who is gone before us, who was hated and rejected of men, a Man of ſorrows, and acquainted with grief; this is he whoſe ſteps we follow, who is made perfect through ſufferings, and therefore are we willing to give our backs to the Smiter, and our cheeks to them that pulleth off the hairs; and to him that ſmiteth us on the one cheek, to turn the other;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117940:9"/>and he that taketh away our cloak, to let him have our coat alſo: and this is thank-worthy, to ſuffer for righteouſneſs ſake, for it is better (if the will of God be) that we ſuffer for well doing, then for evill doing; for Jeſus Chriſt hath ſuffered the juſt for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, that he might bring us unto God: And for this Faith do we contend which was once delivered to the Saints, and are willing to lay down our lives, and to ſeal the teſtimony of our Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with our blood: and this our faith is not to beleeve lies, as thou doth, (which is manifeſted in thy Paper ſufficiently) and this is that faith which overcomes, and gives victory over the world, and beleeves in the Truth as it is in Jeſus.</p>
            <p>And thou begins and reckons from the <hi>Maryan-times,</hi> the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations of men famous, (as thou ſaith) who ſtood for Faith and Holineſs, and the profeſſion of true Religion.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, Thou may ſee what thy profeſſion of true Religion ends in, who art now in thy old age beleeving lyes and falſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, which thou haſt no true ground for, and are accuſing and ſlandering the pure innocent Truth of God, which is clear in the ſight of God of theſe ſlanders which thou haſt caſt upon it, for which the Juſt God will plead with thee, when thy talking of a Faith will not ſerve thee, nor thy profeſſion of a true Religion, when thou art perſecuting and detaining the pure Religion, and undefiled before God and the Father; this is to viſit the Father leſs and the Widow in their affliction, and to keep himſelf unſpotted of the world: But thou art found in the deſilement, and caſting thy filth of lyes and ſlanders upon Religion, and therefore art thou found in the world, one of them. Therefore now repent of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill of thy doings while thou haſt time, and turn thy minde to that meaſure of God in thee, which tells thee thou ſhould not lye nor ſlander, nor accuſe falſly; there is ſomething in thee that tells thee theſe things ought not to be; there is that of God in thy conſcience which tells thee thou ought not to beleeve lyes, nor to take re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports from the mouths of ſlanderers, and to caſt them upon the innocent (who was ever reproached and ſlandered by the world) and ſo in this thou art become one with the perſecutors that ever perſecuted the appearance of God, where ever it was made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. So let that of God in thy conſcience now examine and ſearch what thou art doing, who art ſlandering thoſe whom thou knows not, nor hath nothing to lay to their charge, but what thou hath by hear-ſay, and conſider whether this be as thou would be done by. But in this thou haſt manifeſted thy ignorance of God, and of his pure Truth, which leads to do unto all men, as they would have men to do unto them; and here thou art found out of the Truth, and out of the Life that gave forth the Scriptures, who
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117940:9"/>takes the Scriptures but for a cloak to cover thy nakedneſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, but art ignorant of that ſpirit that ſpoke them forth, as thou makes it manifeſt in thy next words, where thou ſaith, <hi>Thoſe men gave not their mindes with Balaam, to look out for viſions to curſe Gods people.</hi> Here thou haſt manifeſted thy ignorance of the Scriptures, for when <hi>Balaam</hi> looked out at the temptation of <hi>Baalack,</hi> he would have curſed them; but he did not look then to the viſion of God, which ſaid he ſhould not curſe them. And ſo all who wil but read that Scripture, may ſee thy confuſion and ignorance, for in that <hi>Viſion</hi> and <hi>Propheſie, Balaam</hi> did ſee and know the people of God, and could not curſe them while he kept to it, untill he did hearken and look out at the temptation of <hi>Balaack:</hi> And ſo here read thy ignorance in Scripture: Beſides in this thou ſpeaks againſt all the Holy-Men of God, as <hi>Moſes, Samuel, Nathan; Daniel, Iſaiah, Paul, Peter, Iohn, &amp;c.</hi> and all that ever was taught by the immediate Spirit of the living God, was taught by Viſion and Revelation; and this thou exhorts thoſe, whom thou calls the <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> from. Therefore let all that reads thy words, mark thy <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> and ignorance of God, and of his eternall living <hi>Truth,</hi> as it is in Jeſus the only begotten Son, which now the <hi>Father</hi> is revealing in this his day; and the <hi>Son</hi> likewiſe is revealing the <hi>Father; Glory and Praiſes be to the living powerfull God for ever.</hi> And thou ſpeaks of railing againſt Magiſtrates and Miniſters, which is a falſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, for railing we do deny; but we ſpeak the <hi>Truth</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and lye not, our conſciences alſo bearing us witneſs in the ſight of God: And the Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt</hi> we own, who are Miniſters of the Spirit, and not of the Letter, for the Letter killeth, but the Spirit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth alive; and thoſe who have the Miniſtration of the Spirit, which quickens, we own, and have unity with them, who is made not by the will of man, nor the will of the fleſh, but by the wil of God, according to the Promiſe of life which is in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus;</hi> who have not received their Goſpel by man, but by the Revelation of <hi>Ieſus;</hi> this Miniſtry we own, and this Miniſtry we witneſs. But that Miniſtry which is received from man, who teacheth for Doctrine the Precepts and Commandments of men, which are found in the ſteps of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> which <hi>Chriſt</hi> cryed wo againſt, who ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeat, who are ſayers, but not doers; <hi>who bindes hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy burthens grievous to be born, but will not themſelves move them with one of their fingers, but all their works they do to be ſeen of men, love the uppermoſt rooms at Feaſts, the chief ſeats in the Synagogues, are called of men Maſter, who devour widows houſes, and for a pretence make long Prayers; who are blinde guides,</hi> ſuch as Chriſt Jeſus cryed wo againſt, who is our Lord and Maſter, and Shepherd of our ſouls; but who are found acting in thoſe things which he cryed wo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117940:10"/>we do deny, and turn from them, for <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> hath left us a Rule to know them by their fruits, which makes them mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to be <hi>the ravening wolves inwardly,</hi> which <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> ſpeaks of, who have the <hi>Sheeps clothing,</hi> (the Saints words and profeſſion) but their ravening wolviſh nature appears by their perſecution and tyranny, which they exerciſe in this Nation of <hi>England,</hi> as moſt Goals in this Nation can witneſs, who have many of the innocent harmleſs people of God ſhut up in Dungeons and Holes, for no other cauſe but for bearing witneſs for the living God againſt the deceit, by which they keep poor people in blindneſs and ignorance of God, who are the ſame as ever the Lord ſent his true <hi>Prophets</hi> to cry againſt, <hi>who bear rule by their means, and commit the horrible and filthy thing,</hi> which the Lord ſent <hi>Ieremiah</hi> to cry againſt: And, <hi>who ſeek for their Gain from their quarter, and preacheth for Hire,</hi> which the Lord ſent <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to cry againſt; <hi>who feed with the ſat, and clothe with the wool,</hi> which the Lord ſent <hi>Ezekiel</hi> to cry againſt: And, <hi>ſuch as make the people to erre, that bite with their teeth, and cry, Peace, Peace, and he that putteth not into their mouth, they even prepare war againſt them;</hi> which the Lord ſent <hi>Micah</hi> to cry againſt: And <hi>thoſe that ſeduce the people, ſaying, Peace, and there is no peace; and one builds a wall, and another daubs with untempered morter,</hi> thoſe whom the Lord declared againſt by <hi>Ezekiel:</hi> And thoſe whom the Lord ſaith he is againſt, <hi>who propheſie falſe Dreams, and cauſe the people to erre by their lyes and by their lightneſs, and ſay the Lord ſaith it, when, ſaith the Lord, I never ſpake to them.</hi> Theſe are they whom we teſtifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, which all the true <hi>Prophets</hi> of the Lord were ſent to bear witneſs againſt, and therefore by them did they ſuffer, and were called before Magiſtrates and Rulers, and perſecuted and hated of all men, and made as the off-ſcouring of the world, and account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not worthy to live. The ſame Teſtimony, and the ſame Effects and Fruits of it in this Generation (we, who are of the world in ſcorn called Quakers) do witneſs at this day in theſe Nations, as many priſons and ſtockings, and ſcourgings, and whippings we have ſuffered, which is our joy and riches, which ſuffering is not worthy to be compared to the glory which is to be revealed: And bleſſed be our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who hath found us worthy, and given us power, not only to beleeve on him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake; and the Scriptures of everlaſting truth is fulfilled, which hath ſaid, <hi>He was numbred among the tranſgreſſors, and counted as Sheep for the ſlaughter, and killed all the day long;</hi> and this we witneſs to be out portion from this generation, which goes by the name of Miniſters; and for no other cauſe that they have againſt us, but for bearing witneſs for the living God and his Truth, as it is made manifeſt in us by the ſame Spirit, and Life and Power as all the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117940:10"/>Holy Men of God were ſent, <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who were made Miniſters of the Eternall Spirit; theſe were alwayes ſent to ſpeak againſt thoſe who had the form of Scriptures, and the profeſſion, but alwayes perſecuted the Life and Power that ſpoke them forth; and as he that was born after the fleſh, ever perſecuted him that was born after the ſpirit, even ſo it is now: And by this Generation of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Elders,</hi> and <hi>High-Prieſts,</hi> was <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> perſecuted, and accuſed, and hailed, and arraigned before Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, as ye may read throughout the Scriptures; and all the righteous blood that hath been ſhed ſince <hi>Abel,</hi> hath been ſhed by this Generation, and ſo the Scripture is fulfilled which ſaith, <hi>As a Troop of Robbers waits for a man, ſo doth a company of Prieſts murther in the way by conſent.</hi> And for Magiſtrates we own, ſuch as Rule for the Lord, who are a terrour to the evill doers, and lay the Law upon the Tranſgreſſors, who bears not the Sword in vain; ſuch as are for the praiſe of them that do well, ſuch we own and honour in our ſouls, and are ſubject to for conſcience ſake; but all ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and unrighteouſneſs of men, we bear witneſs againſt, in Magiſtrates, Prieſts and people, which act contrary to that of God in the Conſcience, for God is no reſpector of perſons, but of all ſorts of people, he that feareth God and worketh righteouſneſs is accepted with him; and we honour all men in the Lord, and he that ruleth well is worthy of double Honour, and this we ſtand for, and bear witneſs to, and this Teſtimony we are willing (if we be called to it) to ſeal with our blood, as many who have gone before us have done. And ſo here thou may ſee and read thy Accuſation to be falſe, who ſaith we rail againſt MAGISTRATES and MI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NISTERS.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſaith, <hi>Truth is, Beloved, and that which is my grief, that I have been informed (and I dare not but beleeve it) that there are men among you who have departed from the Faith and Purity of the Gospel, to depend upon Ieſuitical and Satanicall deluſions, I mean ſuch as go under the name of quakers, who depend not upon the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for Light, but on what they receive from a Spirit which caſteth them into a Trance, what theſe Trances are, let men of underſtanding judge, for I am weak, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwer, Let all who reads thy words, try thy beloved Truth (as thou calls it) which is, that thou dare not beleeve lyes; that which many hundreds can witneſs to the contrary of this, that thou haſt ſpoken, which though thou ſaith there is men among us, whom thou ſaith goeth under the name of <hi>quakers,</hi> that depends upon Jeſuiticall and Satanicall Deluſions, this we utterly deny, and a Cloud of Witneſſes we have, which will ſtand againſt thee in this thing, and witneſs it to be an untruth (which thou confeſſeth thy
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117940:11"/>faith dare not but beleeve) and among many thouſands which is convinced of the everlaſting <hi>Truch</hi> of the everlaſting God, we do not know one Prieſt, or Jeſuit, or Papiſt, that owns us, or joynes with us: And ſo let all that reads thy <hi>Truth,</hi> and thy <hi>Faith</hi> (as thou call it) ſee how far thou art from the <hi>Truth;</hi> neither is there any among us that is brought into the Miniſtry to Preach the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Goſpel, that ever did profeſs that <hi>Faith</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh Church.</hi> And ſo, <hi>whether thou be not found here in a Satanicall Deluſion, who is thus bclying, and ſlandering, and accuſing falſely the innocent, contrary to all Truth? whether lyes and ſlanders, and falſe accuſations, be not of of the Devill; let all honeſt hearts judge?</hi> And now let any, who hath the leaſt meaſure of God in them to guide their mindes unto Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Equity, judge what <hi>Faith</hi> this is that thou art exhorting to, who art found in ſuch deluſions of beleeving lyes thy ſelf, how thou can exhort to the <hi>Truth</hi> who art found quite contrary, accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing, reproaching, ſcandalizing and defiling the <hi>Truth,</hi> thy faith which doth not purifie thy heart from this uncleanneſs, we do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; and thy Hope which doth not purifie from theſe filthy accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, we do deny; and the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> wil deny it where ever it is, and doth know and ſee that no lye is of the Truth: And ſo this thy <hi>Faith</hi> which thou art exhorting to, when the juſt and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tcous God cometh to plead with all fleſh, by Sword and by Fire, thou and thy <hi>Faith</hi> (which dare not but beleeve lyes) wil periſh; <hi>and the hope of the Hypocrite doth periſh, when the over ſlowing ſcourge cometh.</hi> Therefore take warning, and now thou haſt time prize it, for the Judge ſtands at the doore, who layes Judgement to the line, and rightcouſneſs to the Plummet; and thy refuge of lyes will be ſwept away, and thy Covenant with <hi>Hell</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> will be broken: For the tryed Stone is riſen, the ſure Foundation, <hi>who jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth with righteouſneſs, and reproves with equity.</hi> Therefore turn thy minde to that which is juſt, and equall, and righteous, that is of God, which tells thee thou ought not to do wrong, nor to accuſe falſly; this will ſhew thee the deceit of thy heart, and let thee fee thy vain thoughts that lodgeth within thee, and the darkneſs of thy minde, which thou haſt made manifeſt by thy words, who faith, <hi>They depend not upon the Scriptures for a Light:</hi> Here let the Scriptures try thee and judge thee, who ſaith the Scriptures is the Light, when the Scriptures ſaith, <hi>Chriſt is the Light which lighteth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man that cometh into the world; and every one that loveth this Light, walketh in this Light, and bringeth his deeds to this Light to be proved and tryed by the Light; and he that doth evill hates the Light, and turns from the Light, leaſt his deeds ſhould be reproved.</hi> And here let the Scripture judge and try thee, whether thou doth not deny Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaith, <hi>I am the Light of the world,</hi> whenas thou
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117940:11"/>ſaith the Scripture is the <hi>Light;</hi> here thou denies him, <hi>who is a Light to lighten the Gentiles, and the glory of his people Iſrael.</hi> Now let all ſee what thou haſt to ſee or to judge with, who denies the light of the body, which is the eye, <hi>for when the eye is ſingle, the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is full of Light; but when the eye is evill, the whole body is full of darkneſs.</hi> And here thou art found now, who art looking at the Letter without thee, but thy body is full of darkneſs, confuſion, and enmity againſt the Truth of God, as thou hath manifeſted in this thy Paper. And Chriſt Jeſus ſaid unto his Diſciples, <hi>Ye are the light of the world; a city that is ſet on a hill cannot be bid: Let your Light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your Father which is in heaven.</hi> But thy works and thy <hi>Light</hi> is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by thy envy that thou haſt uttered forth againſt the harmleſs, which thou knows nothing by. But thou that hath no other <hi>Light</hi> to judge with but the Scriptures without thee, which was ſpoken forth from another ſpirit then thou ſpeaketh from; now thou that taketh theſe words, and ſpeaketh them forth from a lying ſpirit, which was ſpoken forth from the Light, and Life, and Power of God; from the juſt and the living Truth was the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſpoken forth from: But thou who hath no Light to walk or ſpeak by, but what thy dark ſpirit gathers out of the words without thee, were not like to ſpeak truth; for they that ſpoke forth; the Scriptures, the <hi>Truth</hi> was made manifeſt in them, they did not ſpeak from another, or by hear-ſay, as thou doth; thy ſpoke what they knew, and what they witneſſed, and bare teſtimony to the <hi>Truth;</hi> and all who cometh into the ſame <hi>Truth,</hi> beareth witneſs unto them, and knoweth the ſame <hi>Truth</hi> as they did: But this thou art ignorant of, who hath nothing but the Husk and the outſide, the Kernal and the Subſtance thou knoweth nothing of; but bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Lord God for evermore, the ſame Life and Power as they ſpoke from is witneſſed, and they that ſpoke forth the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are witneſſed to be true, by the ſame life; and all ſuch as thou who hath nothing but the Declaration of that life, are ſeen and known, and weighed, and all your profeſſion which is without the life and profeſſion denyed; and here is the Lambs war betwixt you and us, you have the words and Declaration which the life ſple, we have the Life and Subſtance which ſpoke theſe words, and ſo you have the outſide, who are born after the fleſh, perſecutes us who are born after the ſpirit: And ſo now read where thou, and you all are, who are found in this perſecuting nature; for I am ſure, if you will be tryed by the Scriptures, you cannot finde that ever any of the Saints of God perſecuted any, but were ever per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, and ever ſuffered perſecution by thoſe who had a profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as Chriſt Jeſus was crucified by the chief Prieſts, and the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117940:12"/>Scribes, and Phariſees, who were the ſtricteſt profeſſors of the Scriptures, which ſpoke of him, and prophecied of him, which that age, and that Generation had; beſides, all the Saints, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Prophets, and Apoſtles that ever ſuffered, did ſuffer by a people profeſſing Religion. So let the Scriptures be judg between you and us, and if you will come to be tryed by the Scriptures, you will be found of the ſame generation of Perſecutors as ever was before you.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſaith, <hi>VVe depend not upon the Scriptures for Light, hut from what we receive from a Spirit which caſteth us into a Trance, and what this Spirit is, thou confeſſeth thou knows not, and yet thou lakes upon thee to judge of this Spirit, though thou confeſſeth thou art weak, &amp;c. but thou ſaith thou tells what thou thinks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now here thou haſt uttered forth thy weakneſs, and thy naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs appears in theſe words, and thy bitter ſpirit, in ſlandering that which thou knows not, for that which tries the Spirits is Truth, and Eternall and Infallible, and ſpeaks that is knows, and beleeves not every ſpirit, but tries the Spirits whether they be of God. And from this Spirit thou hart ſhut thy ſelf, and by this Spirit do we try thy Spirit to be a Spirit of Error and Deluſion, a Spirit of Darkneſs, which hath no light in it; but thy Light is without thee that thou judgeth by, and thou judgeth by thinking, and this is for judgement: Chriſt Jeſus ſaid, <hi>Take heed that the Light which is in thee be not darkneſs;</hi> he doth not ſay, <hi>take heed that the Letter without thee be not darkneſs;</hi> and he ſaith again, <hi>If thy Light be darkneſs, how great is that darkneſs?</hi> and ſo here thou art in the darkneſs, and yet judgeth of the Light; but thy ſpirit is a fallibe Spirit, and ſo cannot give true judgement upon that which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible and eternall: But that Spirit which is infallible and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, gives true judgement on thee, and knows thee, and tries thee and thy Light, which is thee Letter without thee, which is none of thine, but anothers; and with the ſame ſpirit as ſpoke forth the Scriptures thou art judged, and thy ſpirit to be a fallible lying ſpirit; and the ſame good ſpirit of God as ſpoke in the Holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles, which is not divided, but is one and the ſame for evermore; the ſame ſpirit do we witneſs, not another, but the ſame as was before ever the Scripture was written, and by this Spirit which was before Scripture was written, do we judge thee and thy Light which thou hath from the Declaration: Here thou confeſſeth that if thou had had no Scripture, thou had had no Light; but God is Light, and all who knows him, knows him in the Light; and all who ſees him, ſees him in the Light, for the immortallity dwols in the Light, but this thou knows nothing of; and we do accord with, and own, and witneſs, and have unitywith
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117940:12"/>the ſame Spirit, with all that ſpoke forth the Scriptures, the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and all the Holy men of God, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was taught by the Spirit of God; all that is guided by that one, and the ſame ſpirit we do witneſs and own, and all that have that ſame ſpirit to lead and guide them to the living God (who is a Spirit) wil own and witneſs us to be of God, and our Teſtimony to be true; and this ſhall be anſwered by that of God in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſpeaks ſeverall times of the Inſtitutions and Ordinances of Chriſt, anſwer, The Ordinances and Inſtitutions of Chriſt we own, and witneſs and honour, and his Commands arc not grievons, but joyous: but thou that ſpeaks theſe words, hath made thy ſelf manifeſt to deny the Ordinances of Chriſt, and his Inſtitutions, and art ignorant of them what they are, when thou cometh to name them, thou names <hi>Sabboths, and Sacraments;</hi> and for the Miniſtry and Magiſtracy (which thou ſpeaks of) we have anſwered that before; yet this I ſay to thee more, That thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters which were ordained by Chriſt did not preach for Hire, Chriſt Jeſus bare witneſs againſt the Hireling, and called him a <hi>Thief</hi> and a <hi>Robber;</hi> now ſee if thy Miniſters which thou ſpeaks for be not ſuch, and then ſee if thou do not blaſpheme Chriſt, in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he ordained ſuch as he called <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Robbers,</hi> which are Hirelings, which flies becauſe they are Hirelings; thoſe whom he ordained and ſent forth, were ſent forth freely, who had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved freely of him, and freely they did give; <hi>they did not go in the way of Cain, to envy nor run greedily after the error of Balaam, for gifts and rewards.</hi> Now ſee if thoſe Miniſters which thou ſpeaks of be not ſuch; where did ever Chriſt ordain them? or when did they receive a Commiſſion? but whom he ordained did preach the Goſpel freely to every creature, and had a Commiſſion from him to baptize all Nations, <hi>in the Nome of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> doth thy Miniſters, that thou ſpeak of, ſo? Read the Scriptures honeſtly, and ſee whether Chriſt ordained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but ſuch as had an immediate command and Revelation from him, and ſuch received power from above to go teach all Nations: Now ſee whether theſe Miniſters thou ſpeaks of will own this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, or witneſs it, and if they cannot, then thou art he that blaſphemeth Chritt, and defames his Truth, which is pure, which will not admit of any decit nor guile. And for that thou ſpeaks of <hi>Sabboths,</hi> here thou art denying Chriſt, for where he is known and witneſſed to be come, he is the end of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and the reſt of his people: and what Scripture haſt thou which ſaith that Chriſt ordained a day to be kept as a <hi>Sabbath?</hi> wilt thou belye Chriſt Jeſus, to ſay he hath ordained a <hi>Sabbath-day,</hi> which he putteth an
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117940:13"/>end to. Here let all read the Scriptures and try thee and thy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances that thou pleads ſo for, <hi>the Son of man is the Lord of the Sabboth:</hi> If thou have an ear, thou may hear; or an eye, thou may ſee: but thou art blinde, and yet hath eyes; and deaf, and yet hath ears. And for thy Sacraments, which thou calls an Ordinance of Chriſt, this is an Ordinance of thy own making, which thou hath no Scripture for at all; wilt thou ſay that Chriſt ordained a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when there is no Scripture for it? Oh that thou ſhould be ſo blinde, and yet will take upon the to exhort (as thou ſaith) the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt!</hi> but ſurely the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> knows the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God better then thou doſt, for thy Ordinances is beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly Rudiments, which are but commandments and doctrines of men, but it is little with thee to call them the Ordinances of God, who art ſo far by the Truth, as thou art in all thy Paper through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out: But thoſe who are dead with Chriſt from the Rudiments of the world, cannot be ſubject to thy Ordinances, for the Apoſtle exhorts from them, and ſaith, <hi>Touch not; taſt not, handle not, which are all to periſh with the uſing of them;</hi> and his exhortation we own and cleave to, and keep his Ordinances as he delivered them to us, and thine we do deny; but the Ordinances of Chriſt Jeſus we live in, according to the Scrptures, and all the Saints in Light that ever went before us; for heis our peace who hath made both one, and broken down the partition Wall betwixt us, and hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed in his fleſh the enmity, even the Law of Commandments contained in Ordinances, for to make himſelf of twain one New Man, ſo making peace, and that he might reconcile both unto God in one body by the Croſs, having ſlain the enmity thereby; but where this enmity ſtand unſlain, which is far off, and not waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and made nigh by his blood, here the Ordinances of men is ſet up, and called the Ordinances of God, who are without Chriſt, being aliens from the Common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and Strangers from the Covenant of Promiſe, not being waſhed, and cleanſed, and purged by his blood, which maketh nigh, and taketh away the partition-Wall, and makes of twain one New Man. Now if thou, or any of you, do witneſs this condition, then do you know and live in the Ordinances of Chriſt; but if you be dead in your fins, and the uncircumciſion of your fleſh, then hath he not blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out the hand-writing of Ordinances, and hath not taken it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, nailing it to his Croſs. Now ſee whether ye be here or no, or elſe ever talk of the Ordinances of God, but let them be, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed and in truth they are, the Ordinances of men; and in the mean time ſo long as thou art ignorant of theſe things, and of the workings and operation of the living Spirit, and power of the living God; ſo long as thou knows nothing but what thou knows
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117940:13"/>naturally, beware how thou ſpeaketh of trances, and quakings, and ſuch expreſſions, leaſt thou blaſpheme againſt God; for the living God, nor his power, nor working thou knows not, therefore be ſilent, and beware how thou judges with evill thoughts that which thou knows not, for in that thou corrupts thy ſelf, and art found to be one of thoſe filthy dreamers <hi>which defiles the fleſh, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiſs dominivn, and ſpeak evill of dignities,</hi> and ſo, as I ſaid before, bring thy ſelf under the wo. And ſo beware, and fear and dread the living God, who is a conſuming fire to his Enemies, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him thou cannot ſtand with thy filthy ſtuff, which thou haſt raked together, his jelouſie burns like fire, and this wil be as ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before him: Therefore ſee what thou haſt that will abide the fire, for nothing will ſtand in his preſence but what will anſwer to the fire; and this thou ſhalt eternally witneſs to be truth, and love to thy ſoul. And the ſpirit which ſpeakcth in us is one, and the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever; and that ſpirit which doth not ſpeak the ſame we do deny; and the judgement which thou judgeth we do deny, and by the eternall infallible ſpirit, we ijudge it to be falſe judgement, and of the living God of heaven and carth ſhalt thou be judged for thy falſe judgement, which thou haſt given of the Spirit of Truth, and this thou ſhalt eternally witneſs one day, when thou art arraigned at the barre of Juſtice, as thou ſaith; and we judge and bids ſtand off all unclean ſpirits, all lying, dark, Satanicall Spirits, which knoweth not the living God, nor joins not to the living God, for who is joyned to the Lord is one Spirit, and this is that Spirit which we ſpeak from, which leads and guides up to God. And thou that ſpeaks of trances and quakings, and humbling, and confeſſing, and Originall Sin, and vileneſs, and caſting down, and ſuch like, which thou haſt gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out from the Letter, and ſpeaks them with another ſpirit then ſpoke them in the Scriptures; thou that hath not the ſame Spirit as ſpoke theſe words in the Scriptures, we deny thy ſpirit, and judg it to be the Spirit of Error: by the ſame ſpirit as ſpoke forth the Scriptures, we do try thee and know thee; and we deny all falſe Doctrine, and contradictions, and rediculous and fooliſh things, which thou mentions, and all thy confuſion which thou haft ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered forth in thy Paper, (not worthy mentioning) and the Spirit that ſpoke it, we do utterly deny; and the Spirit of the living God we own, and witneſs, and cleave to, which proceeds from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Son, which is the judge of all unclean, dark, fallible, lying Spirits; this is our Leader, and Teacher, and Guider, Judge, and Law-giver, and King: Glory and Praiſes be to our living and powerfull God for ever. And after that thou haſt judged the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God to be the Spirit of the Devill; thou confeſſeth that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117940:14"/>thou haſt not waded very deep into the matter: Here thou haſt made manifeſt thy ſhallowneſs and ſinfulneſs of Truth indeed, and uttering forth thy folly and ignorance of God. But thou art comprehended, and the depth of thy deceit is known and ſeen, and the bottom and foundation on which thou ſtands is ſandy, and the words thou hears, but doth them not; and therefore art thou likened unto the fooliſh man, that hath built thy houſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sand, for when the winde blows and beats upon thy houſe, it will fall, and great will be the fall of it.</p>
            <p>And thou ſpeaks of <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> which was known in <hi>London</hi> to quake, and to ſpeak in the Congregations, and thou ſaith, <hi>Theſe men no doubt might make a Covenant with the Devill, and by the fineſt way of witchcraft and ſorcery convey it unto others by an implicit Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, ſeducing men thinking no ſuch thing, but rather as though God had more abundantly declared his love to them, then to any people in the world, when as the matter is nothing elſe, but Satan transformed into an Angel of Light;</hi> and ſo then thou goes on to tell thy ſtory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer:</hi> Here let all who reads thy words, and hath any mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Juſtice, Equity, or Honeſty in them, behold thy blindneſs and ignorance of God, and of his Truth, who hath given ſuch a manifeſt lye as this is under thy hand, and yet hath the boldneſs to judge the Spirit of Truth to be the Spirit of Satan, at that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inſtant when thou art found in the Devils work, venting and vomiting lyes and ſlanders upon the pure Truth of the living God, which ſhall be found clear, and pure, and innocent, and guiltleſs of all theſe falſe ſlanders which thou haſt caſt upon it; God and his Truth ſhall be found true, and all ſuch men as thou found ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, as hundreds in <hi>London</hi> (from whence thou fetcheth this lye) ſhall witneſs, that this which thou haſt ſpoken to be a lie and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and all lyes is of the Devill, and he is the Father of all lyars: and I do beleeve that thou wilt not finde one in <hi>London</hi> (of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands as there is in the ſame nature as thou art in) that will ſay they ſaw Jeſuits quake there; but I am ſure that hundreds there are that are convinced of the living Truth of God, which will teſtifie againſt thy lyes, and bear witneſs for the Truth againſt thy falſe ſlanders, And thoſe men which thou ſaith are ſeduced by witchcraft, and ſorcerie, and an implicite Covenant. Anſwer; but thoſe men whom thou ſpeaks, as being contemptible, will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee thee to be a poor deceived, ſeduced creature, who utters forth thy confuſion, and darkneſs, and ignorance, and makes thy folly manifeſt: And thouſands there are at this day, who have not come ſo far up to the Truth of God, as to own us, yet will ſee thee to be a dark, ignorant, deluded, beſotted ſpirit, who knows nothing at all of God, but what thou knows it is naturally, as a bruit beaſt,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117940:14"/>which <hi>Iude</hi> ſpeaks of. And thou that doth ground and raiſe ſuch ſcandals, as thou hath done in thy Paper, upon ſuch lyes and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths as theſe that thou tells, let all honeſt hearted judge what ſpirit it is that guides and leads thee; for I am ſure that hundreds will ſet to their hands and ſeals, that this which thou ſpeaks is falſe; and yet from this ground doſt thou raiſe thy Exhortation (thou ſaith) to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> ſo now whether any <hi>Church,</hi> which hath but the name and profeſſion of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> will receive ſuch reports, and lyes, and ſlanders, and give it under their hands as thou haſt done; let all the profeſſed <hi>Churches,</hi> though there be many that can talk of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>God,</hi> as thou doth, and ſerve the Devill, as thou hath done here; I ſay, Let all the profeſſed <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> (as thou calls them) both in <hi>New-England,</hi> and elſewhere, bluſh, and be aſhamed of thee, who haſt given ſuch manifeſt lyes, and ſlanders, and ſcandals of the pure Truth (for a teſtimony of thy Faith) which thou confeſſeth thou hath but by report: But thou haſt made thy ſelf manifeſt to be a defamer of the Truth of God, who ſaith, <hi>Report, and we will report it:</hi> And ſo thou goes on with thy Report and Story, which thou ſaith is credibly reported to be in, or about <hi>Briſtol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There was a mans wife that deſired to go to one of the</hi> Quakers <hi>Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, her husband was unwilling, but after importunity he gave her leave; but ſhe was ſo wrought upon in that Meeting, that when ſhe came home again ſhe was fill'd with Revelations, and ſpoke as though ſhe had ſpoken with the tongue of Angels, to admiration far above her ſelf; her husband told her ſhe was bewitched, but ſhe was far enough from belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that; but he could not ſatisfie himſelf, but would ſearch her body, to ſee what tokens he could finde, &amp; about her arm he found a ſilk thred, he inquired how that came there, ſhe ſerious profeſſed ſhe knew nothing of it; wel, ſaith he, this ſhall not remain here; and he took it away, and then ſhe returned to the ſame woman that ſhe was before ſhe went to the quakers Meeting:</hi> (and ſaith thou) <hi>if this be a true Story, as I credibly beleeve, tell me if there was not witchcraft uſed in this quakers Meeting, yea or nay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let all honeſt hearts, who reads this thy Story, read thy Spirit and thy envy, who hatcheth Cockatrice-Eggs, and weaves Spiders-webs, and he that eateth of theſe Eggs dyeth, and that which is cruſhed breaketh into a Viper: Now if thou be not blind thou may read thy Spirit in this Scripture, but for this cauſe God hath ſent thee ſtrong deluſions, that thou ſhould beleeve lyes; and I know aſſuredly that thouſands there is about <hi>Briſtol,</hi> from whence thou fetcheth this lye, that will witneſs and teſtifie that this is a groſs lye alſo, and that there was never any ſuch thing done or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted there by thoſe people called quakers: And therefore let all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117940:15"/>who have but any moderation, or dram of honeſty in them, judge thy boldneſs and impudence in lying, who ſhould ſend ſuch a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pamphlet as this is into another Nation, which thou profeſſeth love to; but thy hands is defiled with blood, and thy fingers with iniquity; thy lips hath ſpoke lyes, and thy tongue hath utterd per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſs, and thy truſt is in vanity and lyes; thou haſt conceived miſchief, and brought forth iniquity; and this is the fruits of thy Profeſſion, which thou tells ſuch a ſtory of in the beginning of thy Paper, and of ſo many Generations which thou calls <hi>Churches of Chriſt;</hi> but there was never any Generation but might have ſuch a <hi>Church</hi> as this is, whereof thou art a Member, which is grounded upon lyes, and reports, and ſtories; the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Ieſuits</hi> (which thou ſpeaks of) can have no worſe Foundation then thou haſt: Therefore let all that profeſs this <hi>Faith,</hi> that thou art of, be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of thee, and the fruits that thou brings forth, who hath made lyes thy refuge, and with falſhood haſt thou covered thy ſelf as with a garment. And thou goes on, and ſaith, <hi>no doubt the devill can very wel paint men to come to the Lords table and to preach Chriſt,</hi> for thou ſaith, <hi>he hath ſometime been a Preacher of Chriſt himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer:</hi> At that Table where thou ſits the Devill may paint men to come to; and the Devill may preach <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as he doth in thee, talk of a <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and yet the Doctrine, and Foundation, and Ground from whence thou ſpeaks, is lyes and untruths; and all lying comes from the Devill: And ſo let all, who have any thing of God in them to guide their mindes, judge and try thy Spirit, and what Scripture thou hath to prove thy words, or when it was that the Devill preached <hi>Chriſt:</hi> but though in words he might ſpeak of him, as thou doſt, and thy preachers that thou ſpeaks of; but the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>that there is none can preach except they be ſent,</hi> and wilt thou ſay that God ſent the Devill to preach Chriſt? or thou wilt deny the Apoſtles words and Doctrine; or thou wilt blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme God; chooſe which of theſe thou wilt taſte: And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaid, <hi>they could not ſit at the Lords table and the table of Devill:</hi> And thou ſaith, <hi>the Deville an paint men to come to the Lords table:</hi> Now wilt thou deny the Apoſtles Doctrine there? or wilt thou confeſs thy ſelf be at the Table of the Devill, feeding among lyars and envious perſons, which holds the Truth in unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? Therefore expect the wrath of God to be revealed from Heaven upon thee, which is againſt all ungodlineſs and unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of men, who are <hi>back-biters, haters of God, despitefull, proud boaſters, inventers of evill, who have changed the truth of God into a lye.</hi> Here read thy ſelf, and thy ſpirit, and thy practiſe, and thy portion, for God is the ſame, he changeth not, and according to thy works ſhall thy reward be. So thou goes on in thy accuſing,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117940:15"/>and back-biting, and ſlandering: and thou brings up <hi>Grimdleton,</hi> whom thou ſayes came up to Trances and Revelations, which thou ſaith fell at laſt to Popery and prophaneneſs. But this which we have only from thy own mouth, which is ſo ſtuft with lyes and ſlanders, who is ſet on back-biting, and ſlandering, and accuſing, and thy ground is but by hear-ſay, we ſhall give little credit to what thou ſpeaks, either of <hi>Grimdleton,</hi> or any elſe, for we know thy ground is falſity and lyes, and ſo there can no truth ſpring from that Root: But I do beleeve that thou does accuſe <hi>Grimdle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> falſly, and belye them, in that thou ſaith they are turned to Popery; but thy throat is grown ſo wide, that thou canſt ſwallow any thing; and thou never heeds who thy Informers are, ſo that it feed that Root which grows in thee, which brings forth bitter fruit.</p>
            <p>And thou ſaith, <hi>It is the main thing that the Devill drives at now' becauſe Jeſuits have been the chief Fomentrrs of this quaking Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let all behold and ſee now thy groſs ignorance, and emptineſs and ſhallowneſs, that thou ſhould ſpeak things that thou haſt no preſident, not ground of truth for; <hi>where can thou ſay, or where haſt thou heard that ever the Ieſuits quaked?</hi> Oh that thou ſhould not be aſhamed of ſuch idle, groundleſs untruths, that all who reads thy words may read thee to be a lyar and ſlanderer! Thou cannot produce any that ever knew a <hi>ieſuit</hi> quake; and ſo let all who reads thy words, read thy groſs error and ignotance of Scriptures, who talks of <hi>Ieſuits</hi> quaking (which they never did) and art ſo blinde that thou cannot ſee who they were in Scripture that quaked. Was <hi>Moſes</hi> a <hi>Ieſuit,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>I exceedingly fear and quake?</hi> And was the people of <hi>Iſrael Ieſuits, who came in the morning to the Mount, where there was thunders, and ligntnings, and thick Clouds up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Mount, and the voice of the Trumpet exceeding loud, ſo that all the people that was in the camp exceedingly trembled;</hi> was this Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſounded among the <hi>Ieſuits?</hi> Oh thou miſerable creature! who art thou contending againſt? And was <hi>Ezekiel</hi> a <hi>Ieſuit,</hi> to whom the Word of the Lord came, ſaying, <hi>Son of man, eat thy bread with quaking, and drink thy water with trembling and carefulneſs?</hi> And was <hi>Daniel</hi> a <hi>Ieſuit,</hi> upon whom fell great quakings and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blings? Now ſee and read thy ignorance of the Scriptures, which thou ſaith is thy Light: Now ſee if thou be not blinde, who yet knows not that which thou looks upon to be thy guide, who caſts a Reproach upon that which thou never came to know, nor never was made partaker of: But to an account and reckoning thou ſhalt come for all thy hard ſpeeches.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:117940:16"/>
            <p>And whereas thou ſaith, <hi>That thy hearts deſire is, that they may be eſtabliſhed in the Faith of Gods Elect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thy <hi>heart</hi> is deceitfull, and deſperately-wicked, nor the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Gods Elect,</hi> thou, nor them that thou writes to, never know, for the <hi>Elect</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is pure, and none can lay any thing to the charge of <hi>Gods Elect:</hi> So concerning that <hi>Faith</hi> be thou ſilent, for thou art here charged with many lyes, and ſlanders, and falſe accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which <hi>Gods Elect</hi> was never found guilty of: But it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the portion of the <hi>Elect</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to receive from by genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſuch ſlanders and accuſations as thou haſt here vented in thy Paper, which hath made thee manifeſt to be none of <hi>Gods Elect,</hi> nor none of that <hi>Faith;</hi> neither can they abide in that which they never came in: So thou doſt but utter forth thy folly in thy Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation. And thou goes on in thy confuſion and vanity, and thou askeſt three queſtions, and thou anſwereſt two of them thy ſelf, according to thy folly, emptineſs, and ſhallowneſs, and in the third thou haſt ſet thy ſelf faſt, and knows not how to get out, and ſo thou leaves us to anſwer it; and ſo it is like we ſhall anſwer a fool according to his folly.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Thou askeſt by whom do we hope to beſaved?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We deny the ground of thy Anſwer, and we anſwer from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ground and principle, which thou art ignorant of, and art an enemie to, We hope to be ſaved by CHRIST JESUS, <hi>who is the Light of the world, and hath lighted every man but cometh into the world;</hi> and this <hi>Light</hi> is thy condemnation, who ſaith the Leeter is the <hi>Light:</hi> and ſo the ſame CHRIST JESUS which dyed at Jeruſalem, which witneſſed a good Confeſtion before <hi>Pontius Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> who is the way to the Father, the <hi>Light</hi> hath leads to life; this is our Saviour; and the ſame that ſaves us, condemns thee <hi>who lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth darkneſs rather then Light, becauſe thy deeds are evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Thou askeſt how we came to know there was ever ſuch a man in the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this thou anſwers according to thy publike faith, from a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony without thee; but we deny thy Anſwer; and our anſwer is, That we know that the Son of God is come, who hath given us an underſtanding, and we know him that is true: <hi>And hereby we know that we dwell in him, and he in us, becauſe he hath given us of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit; and we have ſeen, and do teſtifie that the Father ſent the Son to be the Saviour of the world: And we know that we are of God, and the whole world lyes in wickedneſs, and we are in him that is true, even in his Son, Ieſus Chriſt; this is the true God, and eternall life; He that hath an car, let him hear;</hi> but thy car, which ſhould hear, is deaf.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, thou ſaith, <hi>If Chriſt be the Saviour, and that the light and knowledge of him doth ſpring from Holy Scripture,</hi> thou asketh
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117940:16"/>
               <hi>whether the Scriptures be any Rule of Faith and Life in theſe dayes, or are they ahorgated and put an end to by Chriſt? And hath he appointed another way for bringing his Elect to eternall ſalvation?</hi> This quaery (thou ſaith) thou muſt leave to your ſelves to anſwer, <hi>only</hi> (ſayeſt thou) <hi>for my part I know no other way to come to Chriſt my Saviour, then the Holy Scriptures, which he hath commanded me to ſearch, and in which he promiſeth life eternall; and wherein he curſeth all men that addeth to, or detracteth from them: what you have to ſay to theſe things I know not, but this I know, that no man ſpeaking by the Spirit of God, calleth Ieſus execrable; and what do they elſe that-vilifie and ſlight his word and Ordinances, and depends upon a Spirit which croſſeth and contradicteth Chriſt, and his word and Ordinances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer:</hi> In this quaery thou haſt given a Teſtimony of thy Light, and of thy Spirit, and of thy Way, and of thy Faith, and of thy God; for thou haſt taken Chriſt Jeſus among the reſt, and hath belyed him in plain words, now in the latter end of thy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: And thou art ſo blind, led with the God of the world, which hath ſo blinded thy eye; ſure thou thinks all looks with that blind eye as thou doth: Thou confeſſeth that thou haſt none other Light but the Scriptures, and yet thou art run away from it, and art now adding to it, and thou ſaith thy ſelf, <hi>he curſeth all men that addeth to it:</hi> therefore own thy portion now when thou ſeeth thy ſelf there, for thou art now ſo blinde thou ſees not where thou art, but when thou cometh to a ſearch thou wilt finde thy ſelf there: Where is it that Chriſt promiſeth thee eternall life in ſearching the Scriptures? Doth not Chriſt ſay in the verſe before, <hi>Ye have not his word abiding in you, for whom he hath ſent, him ye believe not?</hi> Thou haſt made it manifeſt what life thou haſt; but it is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſeeing thou haſt no other Light, nor no other Way to come to Salvation, nor no other life, but what thou haſt out of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Thou art dead in ſin, but it is no wonder: Oh that thou dare ſo belye Chriſt Jeſus! Doth not that Scripture ſay, on which thou builds theſe words, <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them ye think to have eternall life; and they are they which teſtifie of me, but ye will not come unto me that ye may have life.</hi> Doth he ſay here that life is in the Scriptures? or doth he ſay that he is the Scriptures, when he ſaith, <hi>ye will not come to me that ye may have life?</hi> And art not thou here found thinking to have eternall life in the Scriptures, and wilt not come to Chriſt that thou may have life? and this he ſpoke to the Scribes and Phariſees, who were in the ſame life that thou art in, to whom he ſaid, they had neither heard his voice at any time, nor ſeen his ſhape; but this is all the life that thou knows. And thou ſpeaks of god walking in the midſt of the ſeven Golden Candleſticks; but he doth not walk in the midſt of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117940:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>the midſt of thy Candleſticks, who hath no Light but the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and before thou ſee the ſeven Golden Candleſticks, and he that walks in the midſt of them, thou muſt be turned from where thou art: if thou haſt an ear, thou may hear what the Spirit ſaith. And thou ſaith, this is thy light and thy way to ſalvation, and thou confeſſeth thou knows none other: Anſwer, This hath all drunkards, and all prophane perſons that hath the Scriptures, hath that which thou hath; and if it brings ſalvation to thee, then it brings ſalvation to them; and ſo ſee what a publike faith thou art of: Now ſee whether thou be not in the broad way that leadeth to deſtruction; and now this is thy Teſtimony, and this is thy Light (that we are ſpeaking of all this while) and this is thy way; but this way we do deny; for thou, and all who are where thou art, are gone out of the way, and there is none of you that doth good, no not one: And Chriſt Jeſus (who was before <hi>Abraham,</hi> and before the Scripture was written) is our Light, and our Way, and our Rule, and our Truth, and our Life; and this is life eternall to know the onely true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent; and this life is in his Son: and he that beleeveth on the Son of God, hath the witneſs in himſelf; and he that beleeveth not God, hath made him a lyar, becauſe he beleeved not the Record that God gave of his Son; and this is the Record, that God hath given unto us eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life: And thou that hath no life but what is in the Scriptures, hath not the Record of God, for the Record of God is eternall life; and he that hath the Son, hath life; and he that hath not the Son, hath not life; and this we witneſs fulfilled and manifeſted in us. And ſo now read, and ſee where thou art, who knows no life but the Scriptures, and ſaith that Chriſt hath promiſed eternall life in the Scriptures; and here thou haſt manifeſted thy ſelf not to beleeve the Record that God hath given of his Son, and ſo makes God a lyar. And Chriſt Jeſus is the Light, and Way, and Life, and ever was, of all his children: But thou, and all who looks upon the Scriptures to be the Way, and Light, and Life, hath found out another Way, and hath wreſted the Scriptures to your own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and abrogated them (as thou ſpeaks) and denies the end for which they were given forth, which is, for the perfecting of the Man of God; and ſo here thou art found preaching another Goſpel then Chriſt Jeſus and the Apoſtles did, and art to be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den accurſed. And here thou art found tottering upon a ſandy Foundation, whereon thou cannot ſtand; but the Rock on which the whole <hi>Church</hi> is built, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> of whom all the <hi>Prophets</hi> bears witneſs, and on whom all the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles</hi> is built, do we ſtand unmoveable. And he who was the <hi>faithfull and true VVitneſs, who was dead, is alive, whoſe Name is called, the VVord
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117940:17"/>of God, which VVord was in the beginning, by which VVord the worlds were made; and without him nothing was made that was made; he is riſon, who teacheth his people himſelf, who is the Shepherd of his ſheep, who hath given his life for his ſheep, who doth give unto his ſheep eternall life:</hi> But thou art none of his ſheep, who faith eternal life is in the Scriptures. And upon this Rock of Ages doth the quakers ſtand, which thou haſt uttered forth and vented ſo much envie and reproach upon: Upon this Rock on which they ſtand, ſhalt thou, and all ſuch Profeſlion as thou lives in, and all your feigned Humiliation, and feigned Faith, and periſhing Hope; upon this Rock ſhall you all be daſhed to pieces. And though thou makes a ſcorn and a ſcoff of quaking and trembling, yet <hi>before him ſhall all Nations tremble, and the Rocks rend, and the Mountains melt, and the Hills be removed, for he is riſen that ſhakes terribly the earth;</hi> but this thou art ignorant of, who art not yet come ſo far as the Devills, who do beleeve and tremble; and before ever thou do know the living God, and Jeſus Chriſt to be thy Saviour, thou ſhalt witneſs quaking, and ſhaking down thy unclean nature, which is now head in thee; and if ever thou come to hear, the dreadfull voice of the Almighty, it will make thy filthy, lying, deceitfull Spirit (that ſpeaks in the) to ſhake and quake, <hi>for dreadfull is the Lord to the wicked;</hi> and all that can be ſhaken muſt be done away, that, that which cannot be ſhaken may remain. But though thou talk and profeſſeth the Scripture in words, yet thou art utterly ignorant of them, and the plain words that they ſpeak; and this that thou calls thy light, and thy Life, and thy Rule, thou ſhalt finde wil come to utter ruine (when Chriſt Jeſus, who is the Corner-Stone which all ye builders refuſeth and diſallows) ſhall ſtand and endure for ever, though he be for a Stone of ſtumbling, and a Rock of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to ſuch as thee; but he is become the head of our corner, on whom was are built, and founded, rooted, and grounded unmove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for evermore: <hi>Glory and Praiſes be to the living powerfull God for evermore.</hi> And thou exhorts them in the latter end of thy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, to be ſet in the Faith and Worſhip of God; but hou confeſſeth thou knows not, nor doth not determine what it is, whether it be the Presbyterian way, or the Independant way, and ſo thou haſt left them tottering indeed, (as thou art thy ſelf) and thou and thy Religion is ſure to come to utter ruine, that hath no better founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for thou ſets them to two wayes, to take whether they will, which makes thee clearly maniſeſt that thou knows not the truth at all; for the truth is but one, and the way to it is but one; and thou who art exhorting them, hath thy way to ſeek yet: and thou who out of the way (which is but one) muſt needs be in the erros, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Sects and Opinions, which is the broad way; but in the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117940:18"/>way of <hi>truth</hi> there is no diviſion, <hi>for the light is one, and the way one, and the life one, and the faith one, and the baptiſm one, and one Spirit, and one Lord:</hi> but this thou art ignorant of, who knows nothing but the Letter without thee. But in the very cloſe of thy Paper, thou tells them <hi>of the Law of God ingraven upon their hearts:</hi> Thou might do well to look into that <hi>Law</hi> in thy own particular, and ſearch and examine there in thy own conſcience, and ſee whether thou hve given thy Paper forth from that which God hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten there, or thou hath had it from other Records without thee: (it may be in other Nations.) Alack for thee, thou art rude in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, for thou haſt compaſſed ſea and land for theſe Stories that thou haſt told in this Paper; and if thou could but get one Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyte made by theſe lyes and ſlanders, they might very well be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven fold more the childe of the Devill. But now thou haſt ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled up and down far diſtant, and from various Reports, it is wel thou art come home now in the latter end: Now thou art come to <hi>the Law written in the heart;</hi> ſtay here a while, and turn thy minde to that of God in thy conſcience (which he hath written in thy heart) and that wil teach thee another leſſon then to lye and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and falſly accuſe, back-bite, reproach, and ſcandall; this Teacher will teach thee none of this; but this will reprove thee, and ſhew thee the evill of thy doings, and the deceit of thy heart, and the enmity and envy that lodgeth there, againſt thoſe which never did thee wrong: To this Teacher thou muſt come, and to this thou muſt ſtand or fall, for he will be no more removed into a corner: He is the ſwift Witneſs which cometh near to Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and beareth witneſs againſt the Sorcerer, and againſt the Adulterer and falſe Swearer, and againſt them that turn aſide the ſtranger from his right, and fears not the Lord of Hoſts. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider what thou haſt been doing all this while, and fear the Lord God, and hearken to the voice that calls behinde thee, ſaying, <hi>This is the way, walk in it;</hi> and ſend not thine ear to the wicked, and ſo come to partake of their ſins, and then thou wilt be ſure to partake of their plagues. And ſo in love to thy ſoul we have anſwered this thy Paper and quaeries, and for the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Truth of God, which is innocent and clear of thy ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalls and lyes, and ſlanders, the Lord God is our Witneſs, who will plead our cauſe with our enemies, and clear the innocency of thoſe that ſuffer for him; to whom alone we commit our cauſe, and to him alone return to be judged and tryed, who alone judges the ſecrets of all hearts, who judgeth righteous Judgement, and gives unto every one according to their deeds; to him alone we commit our cauſe, for whom we ſtand witneſſes, in ſufferings, in tryalls, in buffetings, in ſcourgings, in whippings, to whom we owe our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117940:18"/>lives, and whoſe Teſtimony we are willing to ſeal with our blood, if we be called to it. To him who is our Strength and Rock, our Preſerver and Deliverer, be all Glory and Dominion over all, to Reigne and Rule, and have Dominion, who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, Bleſſed for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_queries">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:117940:19"/>
            <head>So now to thee, who hath confeſſed thou hath none other Light, nor knows none other way to Chriſt thy Saviour, then the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, a few Quaeries to thee, and all thoſe thou calls Miniſter, in <hi>New-England</hi> and elſewhere.</head>
            <p>Quaery 1. WHether God was not <hi>the God of</hi> Abraham, <hi>the God of</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and the God of</hi> Jacob, yea or nay?</p>
            <p n="2">2. If ſo, How they did know him to be their God, ſeeing there was no Scriptures written then?</p>
            <p n="3">3. How <hi>Moſes</hi> knew God, and what God had wrought in ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Generations before him, ſeeing there was no Scripture before <hi>Moſes</hi> writ?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether did the <hi>Prophets</hi> of the Lord ſpeak from a Scripture without them, (ſeeing that they ſaid, <hi>thus ſaith the Lord</hi>) or what they ſpoke they received immediately from the Lord, yea or nay?</p>
            <p n="5">5. And whether Chriſt Jeſus, who is the Saviour of his people, was before <hi>Abraham,</hi> yea or nay?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether the Apoſtles had their Teſtimony and aſſurance of ſalvation from the Scriptures without them, or from Chriſt Jeſus, whom the Apoſtle ſaid was within them <hi>the hope of glory,</hi> yea or nay?</p>
            <p n="7">7. And if ſo, what ground or teſtimony have you, that the Scriptures without you is the Light, and the way to Salvation, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that thoſe who ſpoke forth the Scripture had a witneſs and a teſtimony within them?</p>
            <p n="8">8. What aſſurance or certain teſtimony haſt thou, or you, that Chriſt that was crucified at Jeruſalem ſo many hundred years ago, how do you know him to be your Saviour, ſince that you have no teſtimony but the writings without you?</p>
            <p n="9">9. And whether he be not the Saviour of his people from their ſins? and what ſins ye are ſaved from who knows him not but as you have writings and records of him, that he was crucified ſo many hundred years ſince at Jeruſalem; and how you would have known him if you had not had the Declaration of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures?</p>
            <p n="10">10. And whether you do not lay waſt Scriptures, and deny Chriſt, who ſaith they are the Way and Rule of life, whenas the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Chriſt is the way, the truth, and the life,</hi> and that <hi>there is none that cometh to the Father but by him,</hi> yea or nay?</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:117940:19"/>
            <p n="11">11. And whether you do not deny Chriſt Jeſus, and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures alſo, who ſaith the Scriptures is the Light, and that you know none other way to ſalvation; whenas Chriſt Jeſus ſaith, <hi>I am the Light that lighteth every man that cometh into the world, and he that walketh in this Light, ſhall have the Light of life;</hi> and whether you do not deny Chriſt, and the Scriptures, in this, yea or nay; ſeeing the Scriptures ſaith the ſame?</p>
            <p n="12">12. And whether God in the Scriptures hath not promiſed a new Covenant, which he will make with his people, that he will write it in their hearts, and put it in their inward parts; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye do not croſs this Covenant who looks for ſalvation in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward writings, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p n="13">13. Whether God hath not promiſed that he wil teach his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple himſelf, <hi>and that they ſhall not need to ſay, know the Lord, but they ſhall all know me from the leaſt to the greateſt,</hi> yea or nay?</p>
            <p n="14">14. And whether the Teacher (which the Lord hath ſaid <hi>ſhall be no more removed into a Corner</hi>) by which the Lord teacheth his people, whether this be the Letter of Scripture, yea or nay? And whether the Scripture may not be removed into a corner, yea or nay?</p>
            <p n="15">15. What voice that is which calleth behinde, ſaying, <hi>This is the way, walk in it;</hi> and whether the Scriptures be this voice, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p n="16">16. And what way that is which ſhall be called <hi>the way of holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which the unclean ſhall not paſs over, but it ſhall be for the wayſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring man, though fools ſhall not erre therein;</hi> and whether this way be the Scriptures, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p n="17">17. And whether there may not be errage where there is no way known but the Scriptures, yea or nay?</p>
            <p n="18">18. And whether the Apoſtle did not ſpeak truth, when he ſaid to the <hi>Romans, That which may he known of God, is manifeſt in them, for he hath ſhewed it unto them;</hi> and whether that which God did ſhew to them was Scripture without, yea or nay.</p>
            <p n="19">19. And whether the Scriptures without be the Word of God, <hi>which was in the beginning,</hi> yea or nay?</p>
            <p n="20">20. And whether that Word which <hi>Moſes</hi> taught <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and that which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of to the <hi>Romans, which is nigh in the heart,</hi> be not the ſame Word by which the Lord, teacheth his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, yea, or nay?</p>
            <p n="21">21. And whether that <hi>VVord which was in the beginning, and was with God, and which VVord was God, by which all things were made, and without him was not any thing made that was made:</hi> and whether this be the Scripture without, yea or nay?</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:117940:20"/>
            <p n="23">23. And whether this be not him in whom is life, and the life is the light of men; and whether thou and you do not deny the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and Chriſt Jeſus, who is the word and the light, and the life and the way, who ſaith that the Scriptures is the light and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life, and the way to come to ſalvation, yea or nay.</p>
            <p n="24">24. What right, or title, or intereſt haſt thou or you to the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles which the Apoſtles writ to the Saints who received his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, and followed, and was begotten by him, who was a Miniſter of the Spirit which quickneth and maketh alive.</p>
            <p n="25">25. And what is this to you who knows not the miniſtration of the Spirit, but all that you know is from the letter without you, whenas the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>The Letter killeth, but the Spirit giveth life, and the miniſtration of the Spirit turneth from the darkneſs to the light, and from the power of Satan unto God:</hi> and what light are you tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to, who know no other light but the Scriptures without you, which a great part of the world hath, and yet lives in darkneſs, and under the power of Satan.</p>
            <p n="26">26. Whether you do not deceive your own ſouls, who takes theſe words which the Apoſtle ſpoke to a people which was made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the ſame ſpirit which he ſpoke from, and was gathered into the light which he ſpoke from: And theſe words which he ſpoke to a people in another condition, ye take to your ſelves, who knows no light (as you confeſs your ſelves) but the Scriptures without you; and what this will avail you to take theſe words which was ſpoken to another ſeed, whenas the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>The promiſe is not to ſeeds, as to many, but unto one ſeed, which is Chriſt, who is the light, and the way, and the Saviour of his people;</hi> and what is this to you, who have the Scriptures without you for your way, your light and eternal life.</p>
            <p n="27">27. Whether the propheſyings in the Churches of Chriſt, which, we read on in the Scripture, was from the Letter without, or from the Spirit within; and whether you can judge of their conditions then, or now, who are come to the Spirit of Propheſie, who have no teſtimony of Chriſt but from the Letter without.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
